Preliminary Inventory of the Harley C. Stevens Papers, 1901-1961
Hoover Institution Archives
Harley C. Stevens Papers,
1901-1961
69031
Stevens, Harley C.
3 manuscript boxes 1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Texts of treaties, concessions, and agreements between various oil companies and governments of the Middle East, relating to Middle Eastern oil concessions.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1969.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
American Independent Oil Company.; Petroleum industry and trade--Middle East.; Middle East.; United States--Foreign relations.
Container List
- Confidential agreement between Saudi-Arabian government and ARAMCO (Arabian-American Oil Co.) containing concessions pertaining to royalty obligations and loans to Saudi Arabia, 1933 May 29. Typescript, 6pp (a) (Box 1)
- Memorandum of an agreement between the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company of Great Britain and Gulf Exploration Co. of Delaware, USA, a subsidiary of Gulf Oil of Pennsylvania, 1933 December 14. Typescript, 6pp (b)
- Copy of a letter from British Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs Vansittart to U.S. Ambassador Mellon, regarding rights to oil concessions in Kuwait, 1922 November 23. Typescript, 2pp (c)
- Copy of a letter from British Secretary of State Simon to the U.S. chargé d'affaires Atherton, regarding oil concessions in Kuwait, 1932 April 9. Typescript, 3pp (d)
- Convention between the U.K. government and Turkey respecting the Persian Gulf and adjacent territories (with maps), London, 1913 July 29. Photocopy of print, 21pp, 2 copies (e)
- Map showing limits of Kuwait and adjacent country. Photocopy (f)
- Anglo-Iranian Oil Co., Iranian oil agreement. Bill before Majlis. Typescript extract from Times (London,) 1949 July 20, 1p (g)
- Comparative table of royalty provisions (for petroleum) in Near Eastern oil concessions. Typescript, 1p (h)
- Text of petroleum development concessions between Sheik Abdullah bin Quasim Al Thani, ruler of Quatr, and Anglo-Persian Oil Co., 1935 May 17. Typescript, 10pp. With accompanying letter from Fauzi el-Hoss to Ralph K. Davies, 1949 August 10 (i)
- Text of agreement between ruler of Quatr and Sir Hugh Weightman, on behalf of the Central Mining Investment Co., and Robert M. Alpen, Jr., on behalf of Superior Oil Co., 1949 August 5. Typescript, 9pp (j)
- Petroleum concessions convention between the governments of Syria and Lebanon as approved by legislative order #47, dated 1940 March 25. Photocopy, 27pp, in French (k)
- Text of agreement between the Shah of Persia and William Knox d'Arcy representing the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co., 1901 May 28. Typescript, 5pp (l)
- Text of Turko-Persian frontier agreement between the Ottoman government and ambassadors of Great Britain, Russia and Persia in Constantinople, 1913 November. Typescript, 2pp (l)
- Text of agreement between the government of Iraq and the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co., 1925 August 30. Typescript, 6pp (l)
- Text of law approving agreement between the government of Iraq and the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co. (Law #58,) 1926 May 24. Typescript, 1p (l)
- Text of agreement between the government of Iraq and the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co., 1926 May 24. Typescript, 5pp (l)
- Text of Bahrein oil concession, a lease between Sheik Hamad bin Issa al Khalifa and the Bahrein Petroleum Co., 1940 June 19, 21pp (m)
- Text of agreement between the British government and the Kuwait Oil Co., 1934 March 5. Typescript, 13pp (n)
- Text of agreement between the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co. and the Gulf Oil Corporation of Kuwait, 1934 December 14. Typescript, 8pp (o)
- Text of agreement between the Sheik of Kuwait, Ahmed al-Shabir, and the Kuwait Oil Co., 1934 December 23, 2 copies. Typescript, 10pp each (p)
- Text of private agreement between the Saudi Arabian government and the Standard Oil Co. of California, 1933 May 29 (2 copies). Typescript, 4pp each, with 3pp of typescript insert (q)
- Text of contract between the Saudi Arabian government and the Standard Oil Co. of California, covering exploration and development rights in Eastern Saudi Arabia, 1933 May 29, published 1933 July 14, 2 copies. Typescript, 19pp (r)
- "Legal position of Americans in Saudi Arabia: Draft Agenda for a Discussion," n.d. Typescript, 4pp (s)
- Text of lease between Sheik Hamad bin Issa al Khalifa of Bahrein and the Bahrein Petroleum Co., Ltd., 1934 December 29. Typescript, 10pp (t)
- Letter from Sheik Hamad Bin Issa al Khalifa of Bahrein to the Bahrein Petroleum Co. of San Francisco, 1935 January 27. Typescript, 1p (t)
- Text of deed between Sheik Hamad Bin Issa al Khalifa and the Bahrein Petroleum Co., Ltd., 1936 June 3. Typescript, 2pp (t)
- Text of deed between Sheik Hamad Bin Issa al Khalifa and the Bahrein Petroleum Co., Ltd., 1940 June 19. Typescript, 4pp (t)
- Text of "Conditions," 1930 June 12. Typescript, 1p (t)
- Text of translation of Royal Decree ratifying oil concessions, 1939 July 7. Transcript, 1p (u)
- Text of agreement between Sheik Abdulla Sulaiman al Hamdan, Minister of Finance of Saudi Arabia, and the California Arabian Standard Oil Co., 1939 May 31. Mimeograph, 15pp (v)
- Copies of letters between Sheik Abdulla Sulamain al Hamdan, Minister of Finance of Saudi Arabia, and representatives of the California Arabian Standard Oil Co., 1939 May 31, 1939 July 1, and 1947 July 11. The letters from the Saudi Arabian government representatives are noted as "translated." Mimeograph and typescript, 18pp (v)
- Partial text of a cable from William J. Lenahan, dated Dharan 1947 July 12, regarding the Saudi Arabian Pipeline Convention being signed; with a copy of convention of 1947 July 11. Typescript, 19pp (w)
- Text of agreement of 1930 June 13, between the Sheik of Bahrein and Eastern and General Syndicate and of concession dated 1930 August 1. Typescript, 4pp (x)
- Text of agreement between the Saudi Arabian government and the Pacific Western Oil Corporation, 1949 February 20. Copies in English and Arabic. Print, 24pp (y)
- Memorandum from Harley C. Stevens for Ralph K. Davies regarding revised concession terms of Iraq and Mosul Petroleum Companies, 1951 September 19. Typescript, 3pp (z)
- Text of a listing of considerations paid for Saudi Arabian oil concessions, 1933, with a supplement agreement of 1939. Attached letter from Mr. Moore of Trans-Arabian Pipe Line to "His Majesty," 1947 June 24, 3pp (aa)
- Text of agreement between the Anglo-Persian Oil Co. and the Gulf Oil Co., 1937 December 14. Typescript, 2pp (bb)
- Text of opinion by Professor H. Lauterpacht regarding the concession grante, by the Sheik of Kuwait, 1934 December 23. Typescript, 17pp (cc)
- Text of concession agreement between the Sheik of Kuwait and the American Independent Oil Co., 1948 June 28. Mimeograph, 11pp., with a photocopy of Kuwait Concession obligations (dd)
- Text of agreement between the U.K. government and the American Independent Oil Co., 1948 June 26. Typescript, 3pp (ee)
- Translation of Arabic text of the agreement between the American Independent Oil Co. and the Sheik of Kuwait, 1948 June 28. Typescript, 19pp; with comments on the translation by the translator, Dr. Dorothy Stehle, Library of Congress, 1948 November 2. Typescript, 5pp (ff)
- Map of oil concessions in the Middle East, 1960, from World of Petroleum, New York (gg)
- Text of "Summary of Agreement and Documents Comprising Red Line Agreements, a Foreign Office Agreement, 1914, Regarding Arrangements for the Fusion of Interests in Turkish Petroleum Concessions: An Arrangement between the Imperial German Government, the U.K. Government, the National Bank of Turkey, and the Anglo-Saxon Petroleum Co., London, 1914 March 19." Copies of correspondence related to this matter. Typescript, 25pp; with one map of the Red Line agreement area (hh)
- Text of agreement between the National Iranian Oil Co. of Tehran and AGIP Minraria Co. of Milan. Ditto n.d., 2 copies (copy 14 and 19 of 40,) 26pp (ii)
- Text of proclamation of the Sheik of Kuwait regarding off-coast oil drillings, 1949 June 12. Typescript, 1p (jj)
- Text of notes regarding concessions. Typescript, 3pp (jj)
- Printed copy of change in Kuwait income tax regulations. Sample form of agreement between the Sheik of Kuwait and nn. co. Mimeograph, 41pp (jj)
- Text of agreement between Abdul Majid Mahamoud, Minister of Economics of the government of Iraq, and Horace Stephen Gibson, representing: Iraq Petroleum Co., Ltd., Mosul Petroleum Co., Ltd., and Basrah Petroleum Company, 1952 February 3. Typescript, 2 copies, 25pp (kk)
- Manuscript of "History of Operations of the Pacific Western Oil Co. in Saudi Arabia - Kuwait Neutral Zone," Vol. I. "Background of the Saudi Arabian - Kuwait Zone," by Edward Hoagland Brown, 1954. Typescript, 125pp (ll)
- Agreement between the Saudi Arabian government and the Pacific Oil Corporation, n.d. Photocopy of typescript, 32pp (mm)
- Texts of various oil concessions in the Middle East. Typescript (nn)
- Arabian American Oil Co. - Saudi Arabia, 1933 May 29 (nn)
- Arabian American Oil Co. - Saudi Arabia, 1939 (nn)
- Kuwait Oil Co. - Kuwait, concessions, 1933 December 23 (nn)
- Sheik of Bahrein - Bahrein Petroleum Co.; Concessions, 1929 and 1940 (nn)
- American Independent Oil Co.; U.K. Concession in Kuwait, 1948 September 21, 1949 (nn)
- Western Pacific Concession from Ibn Saud (nn)
- American Independent Oil Co. - Pacific Western Oil Corp.; Agreement, 1949 June 30 (nn)
- Trans Arabian Oil Co. - Saudi Arabia; Agreement, 1947 July 11 (nn)
- Trans Arabian Pipe Line Co. - Trans Jordan. Agreement, 1946 August 8 (nn)
- Anglo American Oil Agreement, 1944 August 8 (nn)
- Iraq government - Turkish Petroleum Co., 1925 March 14 (nn)
- Iraq-Basrah Petroleum Co., 1938 July 29 (nn)
- Anglo Persian - Gulf Oil Co., 1933 December 14 (nn)
- Trans Jordan - Petroleum Development, 1947 May 10 (nn)
- Sheik of Quatr - Anglo Iranian Oil Co., 1935 May 17 (nn)
- Quatr Central Mining Co. - Petroleum Development (of Quatr,) 1935 May 17 (nn)
- Persian Gulf royalty obligations (nn)
- Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd. Pipeline: "Employment Regulations," Lebanon, 1946 December 1. Mimeograph, 17pp (a) (Box 2)
- "Labour Law" (279) translated from the Syrian Official Journal, No. 25, 1946 June 13. Typescript, 57pp (b)
- Palestine. Status of the Anglo Iranian Oil Co., 1938 (pipeline concessions #4). Photocopy, 27pp. Index (c)
- Oil Mining Ordinance No. 25, 1938: "An Ordinance to Regulate the Mining of Oil." Typescript, 9pp (d)
- "Political Agreement between his Majesty's Government in the U.K. and the American Independent Oil Co., a California Corporation, Regarding the Oil Concession Covering the Islands of Kubr, Qaru and Umm-al-Maradim," 1949 September 21. Typescript, 5pp (e)
- Agreement between the British government and the Kuwait Oil Co., 1934 March 5. Typescript, 4pp (f)
- Agreement between the Sheik of Kuwait and the Kuwait Oil Co., 1934 December 23. Typescript, 10pp (g)
- Agreement between the Anglo Iranian Oil Co. and the Gulf Oil Co., 1933 December 14. Typescript, 2pp (h)
- Political agreement between U.K. government and the Kuwait Oil Co., 1934 March 5. Typescript, 7pp (i)
- Agreement between the governments of Iran and Turkey relating to a pipeline system through Turkish territory (National Iranian Oil Co.,) Ankara. Photocopy, 6pp (j)
- Agreement between the government of Iran and the Anglo Persian Oil Co., Teheran, 1933 April 29. Photocopy, 11pp (k)
- Letters and reports regarding Arabic translations of texts of agreements between Standard Oil Co. of California and the Saudi Arabian government. Various letters from H. R. Ballantyne, Snourk Hurgronje, and M. W. Vane, 1933 June, August. Photocopy, 11pp (l)
- Agreements between the Saudi Arabian government and the Arabian American Oil Co. Printed text and related correspondence, 1933-1956, in English and Arabic. English text, 99pp. Published in Cairo, 1958 (m)
- Map of oil concessions in the Near East, Dept. of State, U.S. GPO., 1947 July (n)
- Chart listing various Pacific Western and Aminoil concessions (o)
- Binder containing agreements and related documents of the Iranian Oil Consortium. Not sequentially numbered (p)
- Printed documents pertaining to agreement between Esso Trading Co. of Iran (New York City,) Iran California Oil Co. (San Francisco), The Texas Company (Iran), Socony-Vacuum Oil Co. (New York City), Gulf International Co. (Pittsburgh), as Transferors, and American Independent Oil Co. (San Francisco) and seven other U.S. companies. Agreement dated 1955 April 29. Five printed pamphlets (q)
- Papers, drafts, news releases concerning the meetings of representatives of various oil companies and other interests concerned with the erection of a Trans-Arabian pipeline, London, 1957 March 18-20 and May 13-16 (a) (Box 3)
- Papers, drafts, news releases, newspaper articles, magazine clippings about the first Arab Petroleum Congress and exhibition held in Cairo, Egypt, 1959 April 15-22 (b)
- Papers, reports and articles on technical and university education available in various Arab countries, 1958-1961 (c)